howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
this is the gym rut show and I'm your
host Jim rod
today's guest is Cory Doctorow science
fiction writer and social analyst and
critic
hi there it's great to be here great to
have you Cory
you know I've been following your
writings for a long time and actually
first in your role as the social and
Technology analysts and writer and I
remember you were you wrote a fair
amount for under the EF half logo at one
point I was actually involved a bit more
as a cheerleader than a worker in the
setting up of the e FF the FF actually
got organized on the web an ancient
online service which still exists
I still have an account do you really I
was logged in last night yeah I think I
was too I think I come on to my 30 year
mark in December on the well it's a
pretty amazing place and you know they
actually somehow managed not to do a lot
of bad things that we see elsewhere on
the Internet on the other hand they only
have a few thousand numbers so that's
the way it goes sometimes so in addition
to being a prolific science fiction
writer I think I counted 11 or 12 novels
plus a graphics novel
Cory remains active writing on social of
Technology issues writes regularly on
Boing Boing - how you pronounce that
well I mean you know I was always always
curious some really interesting essays
on the EFL deep links blog and recently
had an essay in the New York Times
titled ironically enough I shouldn't
have to publish this in the New York
Times we'll come back to tech and social
issues later but let's start by talking
about some recent works of science
fiction first working like a clock that
is radicalized a set of four novellas
I've always had a sweet spot in my heart
for Gonzales it's a relatively unusual
format
it's a history-making novellas
meaningful to me first was when I was
somewhat a nerdy teenager I read the
science fiction magazines of the era
galaxies analog and magazine of fantasy
and science fiction they regularly every
issue but regularly posted novellas and
for a kid this was a great way to get
some long-form fiction for frames the
second is actually quite funny something
my wife and I talked about regularly
maybe 20 years ago we went on a canoe
portage trip from Lake to Lake up in
Ontario and we had all of our gear pack
correctly but my wife had forgotten to
pack oh my goodness we're both racist
readers and that we've been quite
tragedy fortunately right act with
Stephen King's different seasons which
was four novellas three which had movies
made out them and so we literally took a
knife and split the book in half to
novellas for her two novellas were made
and when we finished we swapped them
that's terrific you know that
radicalised was explicitly the way that
we presented the book was explicitly
modeled on that king book that's
interesting that is to my mind the best
king book ever right and of course it
made been partially influenced by the
fact that one of my top ten movies of
all time to stand by me which was made
at the novella the bath yeah yeah
absolutely and of course you know one of
the audio books for radicalised has read
by Wil Wheaton who got his start in the
movie stand by me yeah he was a writer
right no no no he was a small child at
the time either right oh yes I beg your
pardon
yes that's right I'm sorry I was like no
I think well was nine
yeah yeah that's right anyway going back
to radicalize as I read the four
novellas I took away the sense that this
was all about about the same world and
it's a world kind of like ours a few
years further along but a bit meaner and
more dehumanized way I looked at it it
was a modest to moderate extrapolation
of current trends negative current
trends and assuming no reversals such as
perhaps might happen in the next
election did I get it your world right
and if so why write about a rule
disorder so it's not quite right I do
think that there is a thematic
connection between these stories and
they are about the dystopian proposition
of technology being used to master
people and the utopian proposition of
technological self-determination as a
counter to that force and I wrote them
without a plan
I call them my trump derangement
syndrome stories it's been a tough
couple of years for many of us and you
know as a writer my practice really
revolves around keeping track of little
fragments of information and trying to
make narratives out of them you know
every day I take all of the news that
seems to across my transom and that
people have sent to me and so on and the
stuff that seems like it's part of a
bigger thing that I want to keep track
of I write it up for Boeing Boeing I try
to summarize what's salient about it and
the difference between this and keeping
a private notebook is that you can't
cheat I mean writers have kept
commonplace books forever but you know
we are all very prone to overestimating
our ability to return to our notes later
and know what we meant you know we think
that we can take a lot of shortcuts and
move on but we often return to the those
notes and find them utterly cryptic when
you write for third parties when you
write for an audience it imposes rigor
on your note-taking and it also helps
you find connections that aren't
otherwise obvious but the pace at which
the news cycle started to hit in the
Trump era was so intense that I found my
permanently and even a clinically
anxious that that I just couldn't tell
anymore whether the thing that had me
worried today was the same thing that
had me worried
yesterday with a slightly different
headline or the evolution of something
that I was already tracking or whether a
million new things were coming up every
day and it was very hard to kind of
tease this out and so what I started to
do was what I do as a writer I started
to make narratives out of these stories
and particularly make narratives about
the role the technology plays in them
and so I wrote each of these four
novellas individually and separately and
initially my publisher tor books was
gonna bring out the first one
unauthorised bread as a standalone book
they were so excited by it actually when
I sent it to them that they decided to
launch it as a major title but with only
just a few weeks planning so they were I
turned it in I think in June and they
were gonna bring it out in September and
then I showed them the next story model
minority and they're like okay well
we'll do this one in October and it
proceeded in that way and by the time
they'd seen forward them they were like
no no we should stitch this together
into a big book and treat it like a
novel put you out on tour with it you
know by that point that TV rights had
been sold for an authorized bread to
topic or the people who make the
intercept and you know we had a big
audio book deal and lots of translation
deals and so that's how it emerged as
this big book and the model for that as
I said is that different seasons book by
Stephen King and this idea that
thematically connecting up four novellas
which are such a good form as you say
they're they're really fun to write in
you know I I like to think of as like a
short story as being like traveling with
just a carry-on bag where it's it's
nothing but essentials and as a novel as
the kind of thing you do when you move
from one continent to another as I've
done a couple of times where you get a
whole shipping container but you know a
novella it's like it's like checking a
bag you know you can carry a few comfort
items you're not sure you're gonna need
and so you can you can build up a whole
complicated tale one that one that has a
little room to ruminate and to venture
off the trail and show how maybe some of
the side branches relate back
unauthorised bread
that the base law holds the story of
some refugees coming into the United
States and treated in a pretty
dehumanized and dehumanizing manner and
then the story switches and becomes a
very interesting tale about bread
toasters bread toaster how does that
become interesting well it's because the
bread toasters have been set up to only
allow the toasting of authorized
versions of bread bad idea you know it
began when I was having arguments with
people in the early days of the iPhone
platform about whether or not walled
gardens were suitable and would lead us
to a good place
and you know people had this idea that
if you were going to buy a device from
Steve Jobs that you would have to follow
Steve Jobs as rules and if he said that
you could only buy software that he had
signed off on whose authors had pledged
to give him 30% of the lifetime revenue
that you represented to them then if you
didn't like that you shouldn't have
bought an iPhone in the first place in
fact I had a huge debate on Twitter with
a Canadian Member of Parliament who was
assuring in the Canadian version of the
US Digital Millennium Copyright Act
which makes it a felony to bypass the
kind of locks that are used to make sure
that you only buy software from the
Apple software store and so I wrote a
kind of sarcastic column about this in
the Guardian called if dishwashers were
iPhones and it was a letter from a kind
of Steve Jobs II and CEO of a new kind
of dishwashing experience high tech
company called Disher and he was writing
in response to notional consumer outrage
the problem that his dishwashers would
only wash authorized dishes and he said
well look people what do you expect
foodborne illness has killed more people
than any other cause in the history of
the human race do you think that we can
get your dishes clean enough to eat off
of if we let you put grandma's China in
there and you know if you want to have
independent dishes for your dishwasher
all you have to do is spend $100 on a
Disher software development license or
dish development license and we will
send you the RFID chips that will
the dishwasher to recognize and use them
but by no means should you be like
bending the tines in your dishwasher so
it can load up
non-standard dishes because then we
can't guarantee your experience and
besides that how do we know you're not
using pirate dishes that have been made
by someone who doesn't want to reward
the hard-working designers that we're
taking 30% from who are selling in our
store and you know the joke signally
failed to land Apple users then has now
considered themselves to be an oppressed
ethnic minority and they were outraged
that someone would argue that when you
buy something that it's yours and you
should have the right to use it as you
choose
and really the iPhone represents the
kind of apotheosis of what I call the
shitty technology adoption curve and the
way that that works is that when you
have a terrible idea about technology
you have to work out the kinks in it and
you have to normalize it before you can
roll it out to everyone and so first you
roll it out to people whose complaints
don't get a lot of hearing in the wider
society right you make refugees use it
or kids or poor people or people on
welfare or prisoners or people in mental
institutions and then once it's kind of
normalized then you can roll it out
everywhere else that's why you know 20
years ago if you had a CCTV watching you
while you ate your dinner it was because
you were in a supermax prison and today
it's because you know you've got Apple
home or Google home or Alexa in your
kitchen and so this is a story this the
story unauthorized bread is a story in
which we have entered the full-on
post private property dystopia in which
the ownership of goods in the sense of
being able to decide how you use them is
really only vested in limited liability
companies and as the user of a product
you are really only entitled to use it
in ways that maximize revenues for the
shareholders the companies that sold it
to you but on the way to making that
happen you have to really beta test it
on people who don't get to complain and
refugees are really the best targets for
that and so the story takes place in a
building that represents a kind of
unholy alliance between property
developers and this kind of technology
developer and today during the housing
crisis it's very common for property
developers to get
mission to build beyond what the code
allows to add extra stories to a
building or what have you if they
promise to build some below market rent
apartments and they do this but then
they also do everything they can to make
it clear that they're not happy about it
so this started with the advent of
things like poor doors and poor lobbies
where buildings would have a separate
lobby with a separate door so that the
people who were painful market rent
wouldn t ever ever have to bump into
their poor neighbors and they would have
their own elevators with software of
course in my story they don't have to
bother with a different set of elevators
they can just make elevators that refuse
to stop for you if you're not on one of
the market rent floors if there's
someone from one of the market rent
floors who need to use them and so you
never mix the only evidence you get if
you live in a subsidized floor is the
smell of good cologne when you step into
the elevator that you share a building
with rich people and the rest of the
time you're just stuck waiting 45
minutes for an elevator in the morning
and in the afternoon or you can take 50
flights of stairs and these people live
in apartments where every appliance is
designed to pick their pocket in every
conceivable way to help the property
developer maximize their profits from
their poorest tenants and so the
dishwasher only washes authorized dishes
the toaster only toast authorized bread
and the washing machines only launder
authorized clothing which is pretty
dystopian but where it gets really scary
is at the moment in which the companies
that actually did these deals with the
landlord structure themselves through
bankruptcy you know they're the kind of
financial engineers who dote on debt
loading and periodic bankruptcies and
restructuring and when all the servers
go down everything stops working and so
now you have the only thing worse than
these terrible appliances which is no
appliances at all but this ushers in
this kind of utopian era in which they
start jailbreaking their devices and
realize that these appliances are
perfectly good the only thing wrong with
them is who has control over them and
when they seize the means of computation
then they have a much better life indeed
but of course that's when the story gets
interesting because then there's the
risk that these companies are to come
back that they'll catch people having
jailbroken their devices that they will
seek penalties under the Digital
Millennium Copyright Act and the
Computer Fraud and Abuse Act and other
real laws that are on the books now that
felon eyes this kind of conduct
and that if you get charged with a
felony when you're here as a refugee you
might face deportation to a country that
you left in fear of your life which
means that you might end up dead and so
that's when the stakes get very high
indeed it was quite an amazing story you
know both the social critique but also
the side of human ingenuity and the
ability to overcome hardship the refugee
who first figured out how to do the
jailbreaks and then how she spread this
to the other people in the story so even
you know in a dark story there's there's
always a corner of life around humanity
well you know I've often in a morbid way
thought about what I would like to have
on my tombstone and I could think of
nothing better than this will all be so
great if we don't screw it up you know
there's this story about the founding of
Electronic Frontier Foundation and about
the so called techno utopians that were
around in that time and the story goes
that people like John Perry Barlow or
John Gilmore thought that technology
would automatically be amazing that you
know the reason Mitch kapor wanted to
fund the ffs was that he just thought
technology would make the world a better
place and when you talk to them and I
those folks are my mentors and I really
grew up with them what you learn is that
the reason they were so anxious to start
Electronic Frontier Foundation was not
because they thought things would
automatically be great but because they
feared how terrible things would be if
we didn't make them great if we didn't
safeguard fundamental liberties if we
didn't safeguard competition and privacy
and free speech online that what we
could end up with is the perfect
airtight bubble around all of us that
are a digital nervous system that spans
our species and planet would be used not
to empower us but to pick our pockets
and disorder our minds and distort our
political process and I think we are
living through the consequences of that
fear being realized and if there's any
real injustice right now apart from the
injustice being visited on the people
who are trapped in these systems it's
that we remember these so-called
technological utopians as the knaves who
led us into this trap instead of as the
Cassandras who
that's about them all this time and who
we ignored who we said oh you know this
is just a distraction real politics
takes place in the streets not on the
message boards though actually that was
the second turn of the wave the online
world is actually older than a lot of
kids today think it is in fact I worked
for the very first consumer online
service probably called the source then
we had basically had online animals
everything on the web today character
mode only 30 characters a second $10 an
hour more or less and they go goddamn it
doesn't sound like a very good value but
it was the only thing like it in the
world so we quickly had tens of
thousands of hundreds of thousands of
abusers I will confess we were
definitely tech utopians this was
literally ground zero there were a
number of us that were also interested
in public policy social evolution and we
just assumed that this all had to be for
the good and so it seemed for quite a
while and basically the e FF generation
was 12 years later in 1991-92 and so I
would give them a lot of credit for as
you say not being naive techno utopia
it's like we were in 1980 but seeing
that there was a conflict in play where
the internet could go one of two ways
could either go to be a great benefit
for Humanity or maybe not so good a
thing for Humanity in the first reality
is we've ended up a little it was quite
a bit of both yeah you know if you if
you look at the history of publishing on
technology and on kind of
interdisciplinary approaches to
technology where people who thought
about what computers would be for in the
world as opposed to just how computers
could be better you get this you know
the whole earth review and the whole
earth catalogs and computer lib and the
Yippies published computer magazine
called tap and so on and you get all
these people who were simultaneously
excited by an in terror of how
technology could turn out and who were
determined to try and steer it towards
the good and that again described a lot
the EFS generation
again that was two still and we were
mostly early adopters and then there
were later phase changes that happen
business thought went mass-market
probably most distinctively and that
here year 2008 where Facebook became a
thing and when the iPhone became up
there this is kind of getting into what
we may be talking about at the end of
the talk but you know both of those
represent a turning point not just in
what technology was capable of but in
what regulators were willing to tolerate
and in how the story that we told
ourselves about how markets work had
shifted right that we went from this
idea of markets being a thing that
should be competitive and should be
constantly dynamic and where companies
were being overturned and where company
shouldn't be allowed to use dirty tricks
to fight off competitors the something
that that really dated back to the
trust-busting era to this long project
that started under Ronald Reagan to
recast antitrust law as something whose
only goal was to prevent higher prices
and where everything else was fair game
you know where we're buying your biggest
competitors or merging with small
competitors that might someday grow to
challenge you was fair enough as was
doing things like building walled
gardens around your users and telling
them that they weren't allowed to hop
those walls even if they thought that it
would be in their interest to do so you
know it's it's ironic that Apple on the
one hand got the capital that needed to
build the iPhone by launching the switch
campaign and making the iWork suite
where they allowed people to take
documents created with Microsoft
proprietary tools and bring them over to
a rival platform but when they then
built their next platform they designed
it so that they could invoke the law
that could invoke the digital andum
Copyright Act if anyone ever tried to do
that to them you know every pirate wants
to be an admiral but it's not that often
that you see it being played out that
vividly and in such close temporal
proximity yeah the the story of apples
is quite an interesting one I mean the
original Apple 2 was the exact opposite
the jobs came to stand for later it was
wide open
Wozniak specifically designed this multi
slot bus for the first peripheral I
bought my first Apple two was a DC haze
modem which is another bit of pirate
technology right at that time it was
arguable legality whether you could
actually plug your modem into the wall
but we did it anyway
and it worked I mean it's even more than
that so on the one hand you have the
this idea that AT&T said that they
should alone be able to determine what
you could plug into your wall and you
see famous court cases about this like
Costra phone and Carter phone and so on
but on the other hand Hayes then got
furious that people started making
compatible Hayes modems that use the
same command set the eighty command set
so you know over and over again you see
the people who who gained prominence by
running roughshod over someone else's
exclusive turf then declaring the turf
that they've created to be their own and
theirs alone and you know this is not
new right like the people who came up
with the first sound recordings the
piano rolls were accused by composers of
being pirates John Philip Sousa said if
the infernal talking machines are
allowed to continue we will lose our
voices as we came down out of the trees
but then as phonograms gained prominence
and broadcasters came along and started
playing records without permission they
turned around and they said you know
when we stole those compositions and put
them on records that was legitimate
technological progress but you playing
those records on the radio is just
piracy and then when the broadcaster's
confronted the cable operators who were
sucking in signals and retransmitting
them without permission they said when
we stole the set records to make
broadcast signals that was legitimate
progress but when you steal the
broadcast signals to put them on cable
that's piracy and then the cable
operators say the same thing to the VCR
makers and then the VCR makers Sony turn
around and said this to Napster right
and what changes is not this impulse to
defend the thing that you did as unique
precious and worthy of defense and the
thing that someone else did with what
you made as being piracy and
illegitimate what changed is 40 years of
reaganomics that made the winners of
last year's lotteries into someone who
lawmakers and regularly
were prepared to accept as the only
legitimate lottery winners for all the
years to come
you added that the fact that the low
friction environments of our network
businesses appear to collapse to one or
two winners even more so than the
traditional businesses of the earlier
20th century she combined the two and we
now end up in a position where it's hard
to see how we get out you know I I'm
gonna quibble with you here I have heard
the arguments about network effects and
low friction and global markets and and
first mover advantage and these are all
definitely forces that need to be
reckoned with in competition policy but
here's the thing until Ronald Reagan
gutted antitrust law companies were not
allowed to grow through vertical mergers
or mergers to monopoly horizontal
mergers and they weren't allowed to they
were bound by things like structural
separation where they weren't allowed to
compete with the companies that they
enabled so banks couldn't own businesses
phone companies couldn't own data
processing services and so on and we
took away those protections and
ironically we took away those
protections and the people who were
arguing for deregulation at the time
said well deregulation will be fine
because we have these other antitrust
protections that will protect us from
the worst effects of deregulation and at
the same time their colleagues were
going around and taking away the
antitrust protections too so we lost
both we lost the brake in the emergency
brake and when you look back on the last
40 years and contemplate how it is that
we ended up with duopoly x' in most
telecoms markets and quad awfully and
publishing and in online services and so
on you don't see that these companies
grew because of identifiable benefits of
network effects or low friction you see
that they grew by buying all their
competitors right and then doing really
anti-competitive stuff right Google's
only ever had two products that they
made inside they made mail and search
and everything else they do they bought
right and and you know Bill Gates just
described his greatest regret as not
buying Android for Microsoft when it was
on the open market
so these companies did not grow by the
ineffable and uncountable effects of
networks they grew like Facebook did
they grew by putting spyware on people's
phones right Facebook bought a company
called inaho
that made a fake battery monitor it
would monitor your battery but mostly
what it did was monitor your whole phone
and send Facebook intimate detailed
prospectus 'as of how you used your
phone and on that basis Facebook figured
out which companies to buy and how to
compete with the ones that they hadn't
bought right and that stuff that would
have been banned under a pre Reagan
theories of antitrust so you know it
just seems to me that if you have a set
of rules that prohibit a set of
activities to prevent certain outcome
and you take away the rules and
companies engage in those activities and
you get that outcome that it is not
unreasonable to say maybe the rules were
working and maybe it's not some mystical
force to do with low friction that did
it otherwise you know how is it that we
ended up with one major I where company
that owns every eyewear brand you've
ever heard of and one major
pro-wrestling company that is the last
one standing from where we once had 22
is it very low friction that enabled
that kind of monopolist 'im or is it
exactly the same forces that enabled
monopolist amande tech I think there's
two different things here it's an
interesting distinction first I would
argue that the low frequency increasing
returns to scale models are with a
Google search and Facebook dock platform
the first one that actually did this was
eBay to collapse to a single winner then
they leveraged the single winner to
accrete ancillary products as you say
Google has only built a handful of
products it hasn't done a very good job
of managing very many of the other ones
with a few exceptions but nonetheless is
thrown up against the wall and had a few
big winners that stopped such as YouTube
that they've been able to leverage the
the one true Network effect business to
take the cash flows from that to build
out for as automated capture market
share Facebook has played so far some a
different play which is again once they
reached a tipping point versus the
earlier social media companies there was
a very rapid take off of the 2007 to
2010 period where Facebook platform was
opposed to the company dip down the
network effect business is I would argue
classic as an example of Metcalfe's law
as more of our friends got on just like
the fax machines in the late 80s the
more we wanted to get out and once
everybody's on relatively difficult for
people to back off then Facebook it's
something a little different than Google
which is it started buying other network
effect businesses it bought Instagram
which was a potential my exactly
competitor but partial substitute and
then it leads you know a ways away from
its core business to buy what's that
which relatively unknown to people the
United States was building a
country-by-country Network effects and
so I would say that Facebook is a little
different strategy but both of them and
network effects in there for businesses
say that accreted on to other things
then two together are particularly
dangerous because these network effect
businesses are so outrageously
profitable they can allow very long term
subsidization of other products in a way
to make competition essentially
impossible would you like to try to
compete whatsapp for instance with
Facebook being behind it essentially
impossible well let me take a shot at
how you would compete with them so when
Facebook launched it had exactly the
same problem that a potential Facebook
competitor would have today which is
that everyone who you'd want to talk to
on Facebook was already on MySpace and
the way that Facebook dealt with that
network effect problem was by flipping
it on its head using something called
adversarial interoperability which
brings us back to this idea of
unauthorized bread and adversarial
interoperability is when a new market
entrance comes up with a way to plug
something into an existing market
entrance product without that existing
market entrance permission so this is
like third parties who made terminals
and printers for the IBM 360 or third
parties who made modems for 18 T's
networks or in Facebook's case they made
a tool that would log into my space
using your credentials gather the
messages waiting for you let you reply
to them on Facebook and then push those
replies back to myspace so that you
could then stay in touch with MySpace
without having to use MySpace and every
message you sent back to myspace was
ad for Facebook and so what that did was
it turned my spaces Network effect from
an unassailable wall around its business
into a kind of Corral in which myspace
had conveniently organized all potential
Facebook users for Facebook to go and
gorgeous cell phone the idea that you
have a company that's doing double-digit
growth year on year and that investors
treat that company as the so called kill
zone instead of an irresistible
opportunity to throw everything at
because if you can peel off even 5% of
that business you can make an ungodly
fortune it tells me everything you need
about where we've landed right we've
we've lost our stomach for things like
third party ink and third party engine
parts and third party services that plug
into Facebook I would love to compete
with whatsapp the way I would compete
with whatsapp is by making an
interoperable messenger that gives you
the benefits of whatsapp but without
having the creepy Facebook surveillance
because what's apps value proposition
all along has been we don't spy on you
and we don't advertise to you and
Facebook is now publicly announced that
it's gonna merge whatsapp's back-end
with the Facebook messenger back-end and
the Instagram messenger back-end so they
can data mine the whole thing and I
would say here's a tool that lets you
stay in touch with all your whatsapp
friends it interoperates with whatsapp
it does so without whatsapp's permission
we reverse-engineer it we have a whole
team and we reverse-engineer all day
long every time they make a change we
make a change and we don't spy on you
and so you just tell your friends every
what's that message is gonna come from
with a little line at the bottom that
says sent from the whatsapp alternative
that doesn't spy on you and all those
users who value that will come to your
rival service and whatsapp will have
organized everybody who cares about
privacy and is ready to leave whatsapp
under one roof for you to go and
window-shop in provided that they can't
avail themselves of new laws and new
interpretations of laws that have been
introduced since Facebook's monopolies
like the Computer Fraud and Abuse Act
section 12 one of the DMCA federal trade
secrecy laws tortious interference
theories about license agreements and so
on I think you seen those
for property and legal terms of service
barriers or teach people from doing just
that yeah exactly
yeah I mean you know a good example
would be car engines right so these days
many auto manufacturers use
cryptographic handshaking so that when
you put a new part in a car engine it
won't work until an authorized service
technician unlocks that part using an
unlock code this is something Apple does
with some of its parts for its phones
and so on and you know they also have
this diagnostic tool that reads back
these codes and the cost of goods for
that diagnostic tool is like under a
hundred bucks and they charge thousands
of dollars for it and so we have a tool
that cost thousands of dollars to buy
but a couple hundred bucks to make you
would expect that competitors would rush
in and lower the cost and the problem is
that because you have to bypass a
copyright protection in order to do this
even though car parts that themselves
are not copyrightable the software that
protects them is and so you have to
bypass the copyright protection on it
you violate section 12 one and the
Digital Millennium Copyright Act and so
we cut off the cycle the cycle by which
new entrants challenge old entrants
using new techniques that Gore the old
entrance auks right that take their high
margin business and reduce it to a low
margin business and find some new high
margin business that comes up to find a
new industry that eventually becomes low
margin and that drives innovation and
competition instead what you get is this
ability to just sit pat right to make a
thing and block other people from
entering the market which is how you
have for example insulin going up a
thousand percent in ten years and
particularly Humalog insulin going up a
thousand percent in ten years with no
reformulations no R&D no new patents
being filed just pure anti-competitive
measures that stop other people from
entering the market that allows for a
product to become more expensive not
less over time that is an interesting
one not obvious to me how they
accomplish that which type of insulin
because not that part of the business to
enter and
so clearly in the public domain at this
point yeah I don't know any of the facts
do you have to know any facts how they
writers has got a really good piece on
this today
there's there's a few things so one is
that they actually do have some new
patents but the new patents are on
ancillary processes that they used to
chase off other potential sellers one is
that they have a history of buying up so
this is mostly Eli Lilly they have a
history of buying up generics
manufacturers that might make generic
insulin or paying generics manufacturers
not to make generic insulin so when you
when you try to enter the market they
just offer you some money not to do it
they also use lawsuits under exotic
legal theories to just scare off
potential new entrants to the market and
then they've got a whole bunch of
delivery systems that are themselves
patented right effectively like the
equivalent of a printer that takes a
special printer ink cartridge and
they've spent a lot of money marketing
to doctors to only prescribe these new
delivery systems and so that allows them
to maintain the monopoly over the
underlying biological so you know other
countries where they have single-payer
it's you know a tenth of the price and
less and you know there are caravans now
people with type 1 diabetes who go to
Canada to buy out all the insulin and
the border town pharmacies there's a
rogue DIY bioreactor co-op in Oakland
that is making open-source hardware to
brew your own insulin which you know I'm
generally excited about but also think
boy that sounds like something that
would be much better left to a big
industrial player that was well
regulated if only we had we do have big
industrial players they're just not well
regulated right it would be really nice
to have that ingenuity being used to do
something more interesting than and more
useful than allowing people to brew
their own insulin layer here to this
idea that cereal interoperability which
is you point out it again and again and
again it's been the mechanism that drove
progress and the actual cycle of
creative destruction and now in the
world
mostly physical parts it was relatively
obvious how that could be done
unfortunately essentially all modern
devices are smart we're done quote
devices at that point become entangled
with technology and enough intellectual
property and security systems etc have
you given a thought to what we might
change with respect to law or regulation
that would really to demand legally the
right to have third-party ink cartridges
or you know a farmer in another life and
I can tell you the farmers are really
pissed off right now
at John Deere because traditionally
farmers work on the ring stuff but
mostly you can't work on a new John
Deere tractor
any ideas on how this could be finished
in the world work products are by their
means we're going to incorporate
proprietary intellectual property
there's an interesting nuance here and
John Deere is a good example of it it is
actually not hard to fix your own John
Deere tractor it's just illegal right
when you call out a John Deere
technician they read the same error
codes out of the engine that you read
they take the same part that you buy
from John Deere and they put it in the
engine and the only difference is that
they enter an unlock code and for that
you pay hundreds of dollars and have to
wait a day which means you can't make
hay while the Sun shines which I'm
reliably informed is a bedrock of good
agricultural practice and so the change
that we need to make here is actually
pretty straightforward there's been a
lot of legislation so-called right to
repair legislation that says that John
Deere would have to provide these unlock
codes and that's fair enough and maybe
that's the way to do it but you know
there are there are a bunch of even
simpler bedrock rules that we could make
that would make things simpler so for
example we could say that the Digital
Millennium Copyright Act only prohibits
circumvention for the purposes of
copyright infringement so unless you're
infringing copyright you can break
copyright blocks if you are wanting to
so a good example was we just wanted to
watch American Gods Neil Gaiman as an
old friend of mine his daughter used to
babysit my daughter I love that book we
have a Google
chromecast device hooked up to our big
TV in our living room and so I opened up
the Amazon Prime app on my phone because
I'm an Amazon customer and I could not
get the Amazon video player to talk to
the chrome because Amazon is trying to
lock out people from buying Google home
automation systems they want them to buy
Amazon home automation systems now
jailbreaking my Amazon video player so
that I can watch a movie that I'm
entitled to a watch on a screen that I'm
entitled to watch it on just using a
network protocol that isn't approved by
the user that is not a copyright
infringement right watching a movie
you're allowed to watch in a screen that
you're allowed to watch it on is not a
copyright infringement even if you have
to use a different networking protocol
to make it show up but under the digital
on Ian's Copyright Act just breaking the
protection on the Amazon player is
itself illegal whether or not someone
ends up violating copyright law as a
consequence of it so we could amend the
statute DMCA 1201 to say it is only an
infringement to use a circumvention
device to infringe copyright and you can
make a device that enables bypassing
copyright protection
provided it can be used in ways that
don't infringe copyright so you're not
under any obligation to ensure that the
tool is used lawfully in the same way
that people who make hammers and
crowbars are not under any obligation to
make sure that their tools are used
lawfully and then you would have a
market cuz I would have in that moment
handily just bought a 399 app that
unlocked my Amazon video and played it
through my chromecast
alright so that's kind of one step up we
could have some onesie twosie
tweaks to the laws but the thing that I
would actually prefer is an absolute
defense against all claims for the
purpose of making an interoperable
product that does not violate any law in
and of itself so that would be against
patent claims trade secrecy copyright
circumvention violating Terms of Service
tortious interference and so on that
interoperability would be an absolute
defense in the same way that's a
whistleblowing is an absolute defense
and we would make that a federal statute
and we would empower any entrepreneur
who wanted to
- VC and say you know what we used to
call the Killzone those billions of
dollars in value that are being returned
to the shareholders of the big five tech
companies
I would like to liberate 10% of those
billions for you all you need to do is
give me the money to make a product and
it would enable cooperatives and it
would enable individual tinkerers to go
beyond what the manufacturer allows and
to avail themselves of everything the
law allows it would sunset this
grotesque idea we have now that we
should have a statute on the books that
we might call felony contempt of
business model and restore the idea that
when you buy something it's yours that
in the words of Blackwell private
property is sole and despotic dominion
over the things that you own to the
exclusion of everyone else in the
universe and that the manufacturers
wishes about how you use their products
are immaterial to your obligations and
respected those products say be we wants
to do what Facebook did to his
predecessors look could you Facebook
could assert various ownership rights or
license Terms of Service rules about
usage but you would say the whole rules
become null boy if you're making an
interoperable product right which we've
actually been through this there's a
company called power ventures that said
you know people have too many social
telephones to answer we're gonna make a
single tool that does what Facebook did
to MySpace it'll log into Facebook and
take your waiting Facebook messages
it'll also log into LinkedIn and it'll
log into your dating service and log
into Twitter and it'll put all those
messages in one dashboard where you can
reply to them and Facebook suit them and
they said our Terms of Service have the
force of law under a ronald reagan era
law called the Computer Fraud and Abuse
Act that Congress rushed into action
after the Matthew Broderick movie
wargames spooked them about hacker
crimes and they wrote this extremely
broad law that makes it a felony to
exceed your authorization on a computer
that doesn't belong to you and the what
Facebook advanced was this theory that
your authorization was defined by Terms
of Service and so anytime you exceeded
the Terms of Service you committed a
potential felony well every single one
of us exceeds the terms
on every service we use none of us have
even read them in fact there's just a
bit of research I think from ProPublica
that found they did computational
linguistics analysis on Terms of Service
and they found that the amount of
technical knowledge you need to
understand most terms of service exceeds
the amount of technical knowledge you
need to read a law or medicine textbook
so most people are incapable of
understanding them and even if they are
capable of understanding them no one is
actually reading them you know it's a
little dirty secret that for the first
year of Twitter's existence its Terms of
Service repeatedly referred to the
service as Flickr because they copied
and pasted Twitter's Terms of Service
and nobody not even Twitter bothered to
read it to find out whether or not
they'd replaced all the instances of
Flickr and materials of service so
Facebook made this reasonable argument
but under terms of oligarchy judges show
enormous deference to incumbents and we
ended up with Facebook making new
precedent and we should reverse that we
should do it statutorily Congress should
clarify that violating a click-through
agreement does not constitute a felony
well this has been a amazingly
interesting digression from unauthorized
bread but that's what this show is for
to dig into interesting ideas that take
them wherever they go
let's move on to the next novella in
radicalised which is a model minority
about a little bit superhero-ish seems
like a unauthorized clone of Superman
gets involved with perhaps latest career
trying to protect African Americans from
police violence to tell us more about
that sure yeah I wrote this story after
reading the excellent book by Matt
Taibbi from Rolling Stone he wrote this
book about the murder of Eric garner by
the NYPD called I can't breathe and it
exists you know that murder exists at
the intersection of racism and
computation because the cops had these
key performance indicators where they
had to do a certain number of stop and
frisks every day and they had to fill in
the paperwork that was then data based
and used to calculate bonuses and
promotions or demotions and black marks
on their record and of course if you
shakedown respectable white people who
have the era of city aldermen
then you lose your badge and so what
they did was they just picked a
relatively small cohort of racialized
people and just shook them down over and
over and over and over again you know
Eric garner himself had been targeted so
many times by this one group of cops who
themselves had no data being gathered on
them they turn out subsequently to be
the cops who statistically were most
likely to commit human rights violations
that would cost the new york city
coffers millions for having done things
that led up to the murder of Eric garner
and so they he got so sick of it that
that day he refused to comply and that's
the day they murdered him in cold blood
in plain sight and face no meaningful
consequences and you know listening to
this story I swim every day for my bad
back and I listen to audio books in the
pool on a little underwater mp3 player
and listen to this story I found myself
just getting furious and having this
very atavistic reaction that I think is
very common which is that I wish that
somebody would just go interpose their
flesh between the cops and their victims
I wish that there was like an
unstoppable golem that could go and
prevent this bad act from taking place
this this injustice from taking place
and that's Superman's origin story you
know Superman was created by a couple of
Jewish kids one of them from Toronto
where I'm from my parents used to live
on Joe Shuster way in Toronto which
named after him Daily Planet was named
after the Daily Star and so on and these
Jewish kids were watching the horror of
Nazism unfolding across the ocean and
they imagined this omnipotent golem
Superman who would go in single-handedly
through force of individual agency save
Europe and the world from Nazism and you
know that is an atavistic and satisfying
fantasy it was very far from reality in
particular it's very far from the
reality of how we beat Nazism Nazism was
a collective action problem right it was
not an individual problem there was no
individual action that you could take to
stop Nazism it took the largest
collective project in the history of our
species to defeat Nazism in World War
two
today we have this story to go back to
Ronald Reagan the story that we've been
telling for 40 years that there is no
such thing as society that there is no
such thing as a social problem and that
there are no such things as social
solutions that everything comes down to
the individual that if you want to fix
climate change you need to recycle
better and never mind the fact that your
biggest contribution to climate change
is probably your car and no matter what
Elon Musk thinks you can't dig your own
subway and I wanted to write a story in
which Superman himself experienced those
limits right in which Superman decided
rather than solving the system that he
has been an a willing in a blur of for
all these years that he would instead
individually interpose himself between
races police violence and its victims
and what he discovers is that he is not
the protagonist of his story that the
protagonists of the stories are the
survivors of police violence who are
engaged in a collective project to
assert their collective rights and that
when you show up and say all right I'm
here I'm your ally that it is reasonable
to expect that the people who you are
lying yourself with might ask you what
took you so long
it might make you account for yourself
in all the years when you weren't
standing up and being an ally that's the
story I wanted to tell Robinson said
where were you when the sheriff dogs on
the children in Alabama where were you
when this happened whoa that was some
heavy vans right and it was clearly
impacted the American Eagle quite a bit
yeah and you know we're gonna have this
discussion in in 15 years when we have
our Truth and Reconciliation we're gonna
say where were you when America locked
children in concentration camps and like
Vichy I think what we'll hear is that
everyone will show up to say oh I was on
the side of the Angels then I wasn't
defending the concentration camps right
from the start I was working to end them
I just did it quietly from the inside
and this is where things like the
Twitter record are going to matter and
of course also be a significant dose
following I think I'll get some of that
too and you know
this is the argument that the police
give and you know it's not entirely
wrong it is not entirely wrong to look
to the circumstances under which people
find themselves following orders if this
is Hannah Aaron's point that the
conditions for authoritarianism are
themselves social and not individual and
while we can celebrate the bravery of
the people who didn't follow orders the
Schindler's and so on we also have to
remember that relying on people not to
follow orders when it's a matter of life
or death or when they live under
authoritarian circumstances is an
aspiration and not a plan that if you
get to the point where you have to rely
on people not following orders it's
already past the point at which you
should have been taking action that the
fact that the orders were given is the
thing that we should be worrying about
as much as the fact that they're being
followed experiment
yeah although you know that's not a well
replicated experiment that's part of the
whole replication crisis in psychology
research a lot of those gold standard
widely cited experiments didn't
replicate well there are other ones too
Stanford Prison Experiment Center also
has massive problems replicating
Zimbardo and Milgram have both been
swept up in the replication crisis
unfortunately later shows gonna be with
Brian newzik on the replication process
so I will withdraw those statements I
know Brian he's a just a guy and he's
been driving the psychology replication
crisis project for some time so maybe
draw those let's move on to our third
story the title novella
radicalized about what happens when
predatory insurance companies get even
more predatory than they are today which
is plenty and people start to go off
take it away
yeah sure so as someone who has lifted
lots of different places over the years
I'm keenly aware that every country has
its own blind spots you know I lived in
London for 13 years and to this day I
struggle to explain how it is
that a country that managed to create a
globe spanning Empire is so bad at
plumbing and how it is that British
people accept that it is perfectly
normal that when you want to run the
shower on the second floor that you go
into the closet and flip the switch on
the electric auxilary pump to get the
water pressure up so that you can have a
shower on the second floor and you know
as blindspots go that's relatively
benign it's inconvenient but not
terrible America has its own blind spots
and the blind spots that America has
that are most glaring to me as a
Canadian who's then lived in the United
Kingdom are guns in health care and the
fact that America can't figure out how
to do what every other country in the
world is done which is to shield their
population from routine gun violence and
to bring health care costs under control
by socializing their medicine is an
endless source of remarkable fascination
to me and the impulse for this story
radicalised came when I heard an
interview with the woman who coined the
term in cell which is it's become a
terrorist movement a misogynist
terrorist movement the involuntary
celibates who've committed several
murder sprees in BO that women and men
by young men who have been radicalized
to believe that because of weird pseudo
scientific theories of evolution that
they will never have sex with women but
the origin of this the origin of the
term comes from this queer Canadian
woman who was struggling like many of us
to find romance and physical love and
who considered herself to be
involuntarily celibate and that is a
hardship right it is a hardship to be
lonely it is one of the great hardships
to be lonely and to feel unlovable as
well as unloved and she started a
message board as so many of us have done
to discuss this and what she realized
over time was that most support groups
are their culture is defined by the
people who got better who stick around
to help the people who are just coming
in so if you're in a message board for
you know X drunks or X junkies the elder
states people of that message board are
people who are clean and dry and when
you fall off the wagon they're there to
say listen it gets better you know
no one gets this right the first time
here's what you need to do here's how
you need to patch up those problems with
the people you love but on an insult for
the only people left behind are the
people who can't figure it out the
people who find love they leave and she
realized she was the only one who wasn't
so pathological that she was incapable
of ever finding love and that the only
other people who stuck around were the
people who were that pathological that
broken and that instead of telling
people it gets better they were there to
tell people it gets worse and that it
was a form of self-fulfilling prophecy
and when I heard this interview it
reminded me of a study I'd read by
Boston University psych professor who
was investigating suicide bombers case
histories of suicide bombers in the
occupied territory in the West Bank and
he found that the biggest predictor of
someone being a suicide bomber was not
their commitment to radical ideology but
suicidal depression right that being
suicidal made you commit suicide
bombings and more to the point being
suicidal made you someone who someone
could come and whisper in your ear and
say if you're gonna do it anyway don't
let it go to waste
and that really the origin of suicide
bombing attacks was not ideology but
trauma the trauma that made people
vulnerable to ideologues and so when I
put these things together I said to
myself what would happen if respectable
middle-class white dudes rather than
murdering their intimate partners when
they got frustrated or going and
shooting up brown people at mosques
started to kill healthcare executives
who doom the people that they loved to
slow painful deaths because they denied
them coverage which is not a thing for
the near future that is the thing from
today people in America who are insured
die slow painful deaths because they're
denied coverage by the insurers that
they've been paying all along and what
would happen in our body politic if
suddenly the suicide bombers who were
blowing up the wealthiest people in the
country
senators lobbyists healthcare executives
were not people who embraced Islam or
people who had brown skin but instead
were white people who respectable in
middle class and male how long would it
take us before we started calling them
terrorists and what would their lives be
like and so that's how that story came
about it was very wrenching to write I
have lost loved ones to cancer it is a
wrenching read I when I went on tour
with a book tried reading from that
story and I found I couldn't do it it
was just too much it was extraordinarily
powerful I mean you got some of the
testimony from the people on that board
was just as wrenching as it can get but
you also explored as you describe the
concept of what happens in certain kinds
of echo chambers and filter bubbles this
was an extreme case and they do say
particularly because of the filter
dynamics the boosts radicalized become
community leaders who you're also trying
to say anything more general about
intense echo chambers filter balls well
really what I wanted to do was counter
the contagion theory of radicalization
and replace it with the trauma theory of
radicalization so I think that we are
very confused about the causal
relationship in toxic online activity
today whether that's conspiracy theories
or radicalization that you know we have
these um you might call them idealistic
explanations right why do people believe
in anti VAX well because the ideas have
rubbed up against them and they got the
ideas they were contaminated by them
they got the contagion of bad ideas but
you know anti-vaxxers been around for a
really really long time you can see the
same anti-vaxxer arguments that are made
today being made in the 20s being made
about the Salk vaccine and an
ideological account of the rise of anti
VAX somehow would have to say that the
arguments being made by today's
anti-vaxxers are better more convincing
than the arguments that were made by
their predecessors when anti backs was a
fringe phenomenon and instead I think
that the rise of anti VAX is about the
trauma of not being able to trust the
regulatory process anymore you know I
think that it's not an accident for
example that antibiotics gained currency
at the same time as the opioid epidemic
taking off because the opioid epidemic
is what the anti-vaccine Spira C theory
says is going on the opioid epidemic is
concentrated pharma companies that seek
profit over the health of their
customers who fake the research and
suborn their regulators in order to
commit what is now ultimately millions
of murders worldwide and hundreds of
thousands of murders in America and they
do so with impunity because the
regulator's who are supposed to be
watching them are instead asleep at the
switch or even worse they're enabling
them because they expect to have jobs in
those industries when they're turning
government services over and in the same
way when we talk about other forms of
radicalization and filter bubbles we
have this idea of contagion that leads
people to believe in all kinds of bad
things but we don't investigate material
circumstances we don't give weight to
the idea that the material circumstances
are what caused the contagion and I just
don't think like so Alex Jones was
around forever right you can go and
watch videos of Alex Jones from 15 years
ago
he is not more convincing than he was in
the wake of Sandy Hook he was seeing
exactly the same kind of crazy you know
non credible loony stuff in the wake of
other tragedies before Sandy Hook Alex
Jones didn't change the material
circumstances of people who listened to
Alex Jones changed and those material
circumstances I think relate to
inequality unfairness and a fundamental
untrustworthiness of the civic society
that is the best hedge that we have
against this kind of activity and
ultimately you know spoiler alert in the
story the thing that stops the suicide
bombing is health care right it's not
convincing people that the price of a
free market is watching your loved ones
die right and so long as our model of
radicalization revolves around contagion
rather than trauma then we're left with
this response that acts like the bad
apology which was the apology that
really dominated our world especially
before the me2 movement and the bad
apology goes like this
I'm sorry you're angry at me try being
less angry right because I'm not gonna
change whatever behavior made you angry
and in the same way when we respond to
radicalize a
our response is often we're sorry you're
traumatized try being less traumatized
because we're not gonna remove the thing
that gave you the trauma in the first
place that's the interesting theory on
trauma that's essentially narrowly drawn
is I would also suggest however that
there may be a broader systemic which
some people call information nihilism or
others refer to as the epistemological
crisis where there's just so much bad
information flying around and now a lot
of it finely tuned to be medically
contagious for money raising money
making purposes that people's trusted
all information not just in narrow areas
like regulation of Healthcare Products
has become undermine how do you respond
to that well I do think we have an
epistemological crisis I don't know if
you heard that from Dana Boyd I think
she got it for me so this might be my
own talking point coming all the way
around and I think the epistemological
crisis is a crisis not in what we
believe to be true but in how we
adjudicate truth claims right how we
know something is a fair or not fair
process to arrive at beliefs the thing
is that evaluating truth claims in a
high-tech society is too intensive for
each person to do on their own
so take anti-vaxxer example to assess
anti-vaccine to understand why anti
facts is wrong but opioid denial is
right or at the belief that opioids
aren't safe is correct which you could
have called opioid denial ten years ago
when the dominant scientific consensus
was that it was fine in order to
distinguish those two cases you first
need the media literacy to understand
which journals are trustworthy and which
parts of journals are trustworthy so for
example the opioid crisis was spread by
elevating a single letter to the New
England Journal of Medicine a five
sentence letter from a doctor reporting
that in his hospital he was seeing a
lower incidence of opioid addiction than
the literature predicted and by creating
a web of citations to this one letter
and then by creating a web of citations
to the articles that cited this letter
Purdue Pharma was able to produce an
impressive seeming body of literature
that made it
like opioids were safe it was this huge
edifice hung off of this one very janky
little Tenpenny nail that they'd
hammered into the wall and so you need
the media literacy to assess the journal
and then you need the statistical
literacy to assess the methodology right
and say well as does this hold up is
this any good and then you need the
domain expertise right you need to
understand cell biology epidemiology
virology and so on to assess the actual
substance of the paper so you can become
media literate maybe you can become
statistically literate I think that
would be great if we did we need much
more statistical literacy in our world
but even if your media literate and you
are statistically literate the domain
literacy to assess a truth claim about
vaccines even if you managed to acquire
that does not carry over to assessing
truth claims about whether your car's
anti-lock braking systems are safe or
whether the reinforced steel joist that
holds your ceiling up have been
adequately reinforced right and so
ultimately you have to defer your trust
to truth seeking exercise and
historically that's been impartial
expert agencies that hear from a variety
of experts and arrive at a conclusion
based on best evidence and that revise
that conclusion whenever new evidence
comes to light even if that means that
products that are very profitable need
to be reformulated or withdrawn from the
market altogether and under conditions
of inequality for 40 years
those truth seeking exercises have
become available to the highest bidder
to the point now where we exist in a
literally terrifying vacuum where we
have no way to know whether a truth
claim that we hear from our expert
regulators is like the truth claim about
vaccines and true or the truth claim
about opioids and lethally
epidemiologically false right genocide
aliy false and in that world where you
don't know whether your next meal will
kill you whether your car will kill you
whether your kids are learning things
that are going to help them or hold them
back we are in conditions of constant
trauma whenever we think about the world
around us we are left with nothing but
the traumatic conclusion that the
ceiling may fall down on us any minute
that our steak dinner might kill us
before breakfast and in that world I
think it does create credibility
for conspiracy theories right that if
you want to eliminate conspiracy
theories that you would do well to
eliminate conspiracies yeah though I did
see something interesting this morning
actually this week's economist said Mike
pointed something a little different
they did an analysis on VAX versus
anti-vaxxer sentiment around the world
and somewhat surprised me I guess I
didn't have anything special Jay
surprising but I thought it interesting
that the highest flow of anti-vaxxer
sentiment in the world is in Western
Europe the lowest
anti-vaxxer sentiment is in South Asia
and we think about who is living under
the most trauma in their everyday life
it would seem to me pretty clear that
people who live in South Asia are
confronting trauma on a daily basis at a
level those of us who lived in the rich
West couldn't even imagine well if
there's a place where that's the least
true it's probably in Western Europe and
isn't that interesting
I'd love to know the ethnography of it
you know I can make up stories about why
it's true but they're untested but like
for example I know that in Europe the
anti-vaxxers closely associated with the
green movement for a long time and it
represented a wider skepticism about
firms profit motives and whether or not
our regulators were weren't honest right
that that was the standard account of
anti-vaccine Europe and continues to be
although it should be noted that the
Green Party has officially purged itself
of anti Beck's elements that they were
really close to it and it's related also
to ideas about you know homeopathy and
so on all these all this mistrust and
medicine grows out of a mistrust in
regulators which is itself grounded in
evidence from lacks regulation of
polluting industries and in the looming
climate crisis and I would say that
India you know obviously India is a
super low trust Society but one of the
things that India values as a culture is
Western processes as being less
corruptible than the Indian state and so
it may be that the view is that vaccine
is viewed as a coming out of a Western
tradition that is intrinsically less
liable to corruption although I think
that's an that there's probably too much
confidence that that's the case but the
idea that if it's coming out of the West
it's probably not as easily suborned as
domestic processes which are especially
in the time of Modi extremely
susceptible to corruption from moneyed
interests yeah we suggest least worth
considering that the network topology of
information flow may also have something
to do with it the Western Europeans and
North Americans are living in a fully on
multi-dimensional multi-vector no
clearing houses for informations we
suppose we're all online might be some
bit too so have to be an interesting
place to law alright let's move on to
the next novella in radicalise which is
the mask of the Red Death this is a
world where the bad trends in the
earlier not novellas may have gotten
worse but in any case the big break
occurred social collapse occurs and we
follow the adventures if we want to call
them a bat of some hardcore survivalists
and you know this one really rang home
for me I'll confess to have had
survivalist tendencies on and off
probably originally in about 1989 when I
happen my wife and I bought a rural
property three hours from DC of a
country farm basically and I said hmm we
bought it mostly for recreation place to
get away you know live a little bit on
the light closer to the land etc then
then life in suburbia I said what this
also have utility as a survivalist
refuge and at the time I said how
curiously should I take that and I came
up with through a pseudo-scientific
process of 2% chance that I would see a
serious social collapse in my lifetime
at the time I was in my late 30s and
pher long life expectancy figure 2%
chance i reran those numbers not too
many years ago a couple years ago and
came up with 20% chance with a much
shorter life expectancy so one might say
I think part of that is I've learned
more about what could cause the social
collapse for instance there's the famous
Carrington effect solar storm that
fortunately hit right before the age of
electricity solar storm of 1859 and then
of course our society seems like it's
got more unstable the last 30 years and
hence I give a non-trivial chance 20
percent might in the next 20 years call
it that we could have a collapse and my
second personal reaction is as you will
tell us when you tell us about the story
your scenario is basically the bunker
version of survivalism where people go
to a bunker and hope they have enough
supplies and goodies to to make it I
will say I never have taken that very
seriously personally and they thought
that if one does want to think about
survivalism you're much better to take a
community-based approach find a place
that has an intact community of people
who have old-timey skills where the
population density is low or there's
plenty of water where the climate is
tolerable and be a good citizen in those
communities and make your bet that those
communities will survive rather than
some guys in a bunker with some guns are
likely to survive so anyway that's my
personal reaction to thinking about this
story tell us some more this was really
a response to some of that kind of
thinking and in particular to the rise
and rise of super wealthy people who are
making plans for the end times you know
you have these this spree of buying
property in New Zealand for bunkers and
so on and it was the idea that
technologically complicated societies
are not the kind of thing where you can
roll back easily to a lower attack
we hear a lot of rhetoric about whether
or not the earth has exceeded its
carrying capacity but what we know is
that the extent to which the earth is
capable of sustaining the life that's on
and today is an intensely technological
question that you know everything from
water purification to modern medicine
and sanitation to energy consumption and
development and the efficiencies that
you gain by having people in close
proximity to each other and so on that
all of those are things that we need in
order to sustain the population that we
have and anything that we can imagine
that would drastically reduce that
population would on the one hand be
extremely indiscriminate right so you
know if you have a superbug or whatever
that kills half of the planet and on the
other hand would leave behind an even
bigger and harder to manage logistical
challenge for the people who survive
because we do have a shared microbial
destiny and if you get rid of half the
people on earth the other half of the
people had better start digging graves
pretty quickly or we are all gonna die
of the cholera that Fester's on the
remains of our former loved ones and so
really the only solution that we have to
a breakdown is not to go backwards but
to go up and through right it's to get
the machine running again I think of the
Titanic as a good parable about the
problems and possibilities of hope and
optimism and pessimism and the limits
thereof right so optimism is a kind of
fatalism right optimism is the idea that
things will get better no matter what we
do and that we can just kind of put our
faith in things working out well and so
optimism is what caused the people who
built the Titanic not to put enough life
jackets and lifeboats on board hope is
why the people who ended up in the water
treaded water and pessimism is why some
of them stopped treading water is a
necessary but insufficient precondition
for survival but the survival of the
people who had hope was dependent on
rescue right was dependent not on making
treading water or even being in a
lifeboat a permanent condition but by
using that as a trend
shanell step to get back on a boat of
the same scale as the Titanic and when
our systems break down which they will
because the law of entropy is a law it
is not pessimistic to think that that
will happen but it is pessimistic to
think that we can't get the systems
running again it's kind of a belief in a
fallen civilization and that that we
have already become members of a fallen
civilization that our ancestors knew how
to build the kind of technologically
advanced society that we live in but
that we have fallen so far from grace
that if that machine were to stop that
we would have no idea how to start it
again we're like the the Krug that old
pulp science-fiction novel who were on a
generation ship who've forgotten that
it's a ship at all and who think that
it's the whole world and who find the
control room and realized that they have
no idea how to steer the ship right and
I don't think that's true I don't think
we're a fallen civilization I think that
we are a civilization that is just as
capable as the people who came before us
of both building and maintaining the
machines around us and that survival is
ultimately about that and that if you go
to a bunker when the lights go out and
hide out and wet the bed well everyone
else figures out how to get the lights
turned on again and then you emerge with
your thumb drives full of Bitcoin and
your automatic weapons hoping that you
will get to live the Frazetta painting
future where your heavy armaments allows
you to assemble a harem and a whole farm
full of chattel slaves to keep you going
that you are going to be sorely
disappointed because we do have a shared
destiny at the microbial level at the
technological level and at the species
level yeah I thought you were bang on
there and debunking the bunker theory
because you're right that surviving some
short period of time during the worst of
the fluctuation is just the beginning of
the game right we have to come back we
have to build some basis for our society
but it's also true and again this is
what one thinks about survivalism
statistically one has to acknowledge
that some scenarios are not sir
people say what would you do about the
10 kilometer asteroid and I go put your
head between your legs and kiss your ass
good-bye right not that we're going to
do about that we're all gonna die most
of us will die with that day or two a
few of us might make it a few months but
we're eventually all going to be dead
someone has to think about you know what
scenarios and for what period of a dip
are you planning for and at what level
can you bring society back to relatively
quickly and you know I am of the view
that under a strong enough Cataclysm
whether it's a biological terror or a
solar storm or EMP related nuclear war
we could get a pretty broken back
Society that falls a long way and
billions of people could die and it
would be horrendously ugly the question
is can that collapse be stopped and
brought back to a sustainable level and
you know we have not forgotten all we
know we're not people in a science
fiction story who or just been coasting
on inertia for a thousand years mostly
we know what we know on the other hand
our technology stacks are extremely deep
for instance micro processors require a
layer of about 15 different very
advanced technologies many of which have
very deep material Sciences requirements
that it's kind of hard to think about
how you'd reboot on the other hand if
you look some of the folks I've chatted
with I have looked at a period at
nineteen twenty five or there abouts
where we had internal combustion engines
we had the beginnings of the of the
industrial world etc there's relatively
little magic involved in the technology
of 1925 vacuum tubes are kind of right
at the cutting edge and maybe we live
without vacuum tubes so we make it 1919
but we could probably get back to 1919
1925 by the skills that you would find
in distributed rural areas
then the question would be could we
solidify a society at the 1925 level and
then from there we build relatively
quickly probably less than clock time to
get back to 2020 well if we're really
serious about recovering from
catastrophe our emphasis should be on
resilience and so it's true that we have
lost a world where there's a certain
degree of legibility right where you
could take apart on an internal
combustion engine and with a certain
amount of for knowledge you could
reconstruct the process that's going on
in it that's that's a lot harder to do
with very large scale integrated
circuits on the other hand we also have
a wider diffusion of expertise and
knowledge than we've ever had before and
while it's true that there's some
intrinsic fragility in our digital
systems there's also an intrinsic
robustness in our digital systems
you know when the Library of Alexandria
burned that was the only copy of many of
those Scrolls if you take down a server
these days the chances are that it's
going to be mirrored and hundreds of
copies around the world in fact we
increasingly have a problem not with
saving data but with making sure that
it's gone and while it's true that old
storage media is very difficult to
recover that it's it's difficult to read
old floppy disks or what have you that
contemporary storage actually doesn't
have these problems contemporary storage
has its own micro controllers that sits
there monitors the health of every
sector and every Drive and rewrites data
preemptively
sectors when other ones start failing
and then at the system level you have
drives sacrificing themselves and and
switching themselves off and moving
their data on to other drives when you
have functional problems and then you
have that also happening at the data
center level and if we are going to make
data robust the most historically
resilient way of doing that is by having
lots of copies of it not by making
enduring copies but by making redundant
copies and that's something digital
allows us to do to a very high degree
and importantly that information that is
more robust at least in some ways than
it's ever been is also the information
we need to keep the system's running and
so I think you played a ball where it
lies and this is the world that we're
living in right we are living in a world
where our strengths are redundancy and
widely diffused skills and our
weaknesses are certain digital fragility
and a path dependence and you can try
and roll back to a pre-digital world or
you can try to make the digital more
robust and resilient by diffusing the
information more widely by diffusing the
expertise more widely by making sure
that things are as legible as possible
for example by demanding source code
along with the products that we have so
that it can be maintained by third
parties to work increasingly with open
source hardware and interoperable
systems and so on and what these do is
they maximize the possibility that
people can render legible the difficult
technical systems that we work with and
depend on today even if they are not
primarily trained in them that is very
true and for small fluctuations
I think it's definitely true I mean we
clearly have many many copies of most
interesting things but it all stands or
Falls around electricity right our grid
is an amazingly fragile device and very
difficult to keep up in fact it's been
proven mathematically that it's
inherently unstable and we should expect
blackouts of arbitrary size we just saw
a really big one in South America
with no apparent cause they'll probably
find there's some small root cause that
cascaded and one could imagine scenarios
where either the grid itself is directly
impacted like through solar flares or
the grid is substantially destroyed
doing during a period of civil unrest
and I think that there's a set of
scenarios where the grid where the grid
comes back within a year and scenarios
where it doesn't and one of the areas
where we have a society been remarkably
negligent is trying to increase the
robustness of the grid such that it can
come back in a year there's a surprising
political figure whose
at the forefront of this which is Newt
Gingrich surprisingly he's identified it
he's written books on it he talks about
it regularly he points out that for you
know a relatively small amount of money
maybe a couple of tens of billions of
dollars we could replicate and put in
safe storage some of the heavy-duty
transformers we can also hi some cold
start electrical generators one of the
few little known things about how the
grid works is the really big plants the
coal-fired plants that nuclear plants
even the most of the gas power plants
cannot start unless there's power in the
grid because they need the power in the
grid to magnetize they're electromagnets
and so we do keep a certain amount of
Trance
of diesel generation around at least
historically we have to be able to do
incremental reboot of the major
generating elements but for economic
reasons and as we know everybody's under
economic pressure the amount of diesel
generation has been declining while the
other asset classes have gone up of
generation and so again it would make a
lot of sense to subsidize at the cost of
a billion or two a year electrical
companies to keep X percent diesel
capacity to essentially be able to warm
a warm boot the grid I mean that sounds
very plausible to me I you know my
experience were on the periphery of this
for example was things like in Florida
the local power authority got a rule
that prohibited people from drawing
power directly from their local solar
generation then requiring them to push
it to the grid and what this meant was
that during times of blackouts after
climate crises that people who were
actually generating power couldn't draw
on that power and I've just arranged to
have solar installed here on my roof in
Southern California and we are laboring
under a similar condition although we
are allowed to have a battery
that charges first before we have to
sell into the grid but we can't run our
house off of our roof we have to run our
house off the grid and we have to sell
our power into the grid and then bring
it back and I can't help but think that
there is an extent to which this is
driven not by complexity but by a desire
to retain centralized control in the
hands of the people who invest in power
generation you're absolutely right about
that I've looked into this quite a bit
in Virginia fortunately Virginia House
either but what they have done on the
screw-you side and Virginia politics is
remarkably dominated by our big energy
company Dominion power pretty much
everybody in the legislature has been
bought off by um Virginia has
extraordinarily bad laws that
corporations can donate to the
legislature in their own corporate name
not even using workarounds like in the
federal system and an unlimited amounts
and so the wholesale price paid to
producers by Dominion and the other
Virginia power companies is ridiculously
low insultingly low however by being a
quasi-libertarian state you are allowed
to run your power directly and I would
also point out it's gonna have thought
about this for the case where you're
mandated to sell back to the grid and
then take it back yes you are mandated
to do so but it's relatively simple
engineering to do it the other way to so
you just have a Frankenstein switch
scenario set up post catastrophe we
throw the switch we're violating the law
oh well you just hope you don't get it
inspected between now and Armageddon you
don't have the switches flow right just
having the capability to do so after
throwing to Frankenstein switches is
almost certainly not a while
though one could imagine a future legal
regime where it might be yeah having
just been through a power inspection
that involved a very close inspection of
my transformers and breaker panel I
would not be surprised to learn that
things that enabled for trivial
circumvention would be judged by the
inspectors who do have a lot of leeway
to not be with him code that's worth
some research again it fits into your
adversarial interoperability actually
right that if you own it why should why
the hell should they be able to tell you
what you can and can't do with your own
solar panels right yeah and and honestly
if there is a problem with the grid
where it is the complexity added by
peripheral generation makes it very
difficult to have this kind of
robustness I think the correct answer is
not a prohibition on a more robust
arrangement but the technological change
and upgrades needed to make our grid
more powerful but unfortunately that's
not a thing
at least here in Burbank that seems to
be in the cards we you know we live in
California and under prop 13 cities are
perennial a cash-strapped because
they're not allowed to raise property
taxes and in Southern California one of
the ways that that's historically been
managed is by sneakily raising power
prices which is technically illegal
those those city power utilities are
supposed to run in a break-even basis
and using that to fund general Treasury
because the alternative was just
shutting off the lights right not
maintaining the roads not having schools
and so on and what happened was a
predatory law firm started finding
cranky libertarians
to sue their cities over illegally
raising energy prices to circumvent the
intention of proposition 13 and when
this came to Burbank Burbank settled
with the law firm paid them a quarter
million dollars to go away and dropped
our power prices which were already
pretty cheap but knocked a twelve
billion dollar hole in the city's
fourteen million dollar budget and left
the city effectively broke and we've now
got a sales tax which is the ultimate in
regressive taxes and tax is the thing we
want people to do which is buying things
locally and
as opposed to taxing things that we
wanted people to do less of like using
water in a drought zone or using extra
electricity and being an efficient in
their electricity usage and now we are
basically in permanent hiatus for that
kind of big infrastructure project here
in Burbank because we've lost that
source of revenue and you were hinting
at and I think I'll go a little further
which is that the longer-term answer to
develop robust this is not just
duplicating these core big components
like transformers and restart capacity
but moving towards a more decentralized
grid there's no reason that we couldn't
have a regulatory regime and if we had
non corrupt state legislatures we could
have some tax incentives on the grounds
that we are increasing social robustness
and resilience by encouraging
decentralized which might not well be at
the household level you know it's
arguable whether household level
photovoltaic actually makes sense but at
the community level you know 50 houses
100 houses there ought to be a national
security incentive for people to build
production centers at that level which
can be operated as Islands when
necessary but can also be operated as
part of the grid in the normal course of
events yeah and so to bring this back
around to to mask of the Red Death here
you know this is a story about people
who've thought of everything except for
the fact that maybe the rest of the
world doesn't think the way that they do
and we're really trapped in a prison of
their belief that everyone else is as
much of a bastard as they are and this
was it's kind of the inverse of my last
novel walk away which was a novel about
people fundamentally behaving good to
one another during a time of crisis and
of the wealthy and powerful and
therefore sociopathic elements of
society being unable to believe that
everyone out there was actually getting
along and being so kind and good to one
another and being certain that that
somewhere out there must be cannibalism
raping and Mad Max LARPing and you know
this is this is grounded in in research
as well the the Rebecca Solnit wrote
this wonderful book called the paradise
built in Hell where she compares
first-person accounts contemporaneous
accounts of life after crises and
disasters with the way that we remember
them and what she finds is that the
isolate
incidents in which people were barbaric
and did turn on one another are the
parts that we remember and the ground
truth of them which is that when the
disaster strikes that's when the
background refrigerator hum of petty
grievance and lays behind the ringing
silence where you realize that you know
you've got more in common with your
neighbors than you have against them and
and where people pitch in and that part
we just erase from our histories and so
walk away was about the other side of
that living through the the people who
are getting on with things and mask of
the Red Death as the is the people who
can't believe that there are people
getting on with things that that you
know there's two kinds of people there's
people believe that the two kinds of
people are good people and bad people
and then there's the people who believe
that most people are good except that
some people are polluted by the belief
that some people are bad well that's
well said and in fact mask of the Red
Death your bunker people died but the
nearby community of Industrialists seem
to be surviving and probably prospering
well and then ultimately you know the
people who are coming back from Phoenix
are coming back and reporting on a world
in which despite the problems of high
population density the advantages of
high population density which are the
advantages of cities all over which is
that you have a whole bunch of different
skills and ideas all rubbing up against
each other make it the place where
civilization is coming back power
generation antibiotic production and so
on you know London during that the
plague ears
would periodically be depopulated by
massive massive fractions you know 25 30
percent even more and then people would
just come back to London despite the
epidemiological problems of close
quarters because the advantages of close
quarters the vibrancy the mixing
together ideas in the speed of progress
overweight the costs and ultimately
we're the answer to the cost right it
was it took a John Snow to create modern
epidemiology but Jon Snow was in London
because London was the kind of place you
went to if you are a person like John
Snow
yeah that's useful
and and hopeful way to look at it I've
really enjoyed this
than just where I was hoping it would be
a really interesting back and forth with
somebody who has clearly thought a hell
of a lot about these things production
services and audio editing by Stanton
Media Lab music by Tom Muller at modern
space music com
[Music]
you